Well, today I wanted to talk about exchanges and clearing
houses, primarily stock exchanges.
So, these are places where shares in
corporations are traded.
And I think it's good to
devote a whole session to them
because exchange is central to economics.
In fact, I was struck recently, I was rereading the
presidential address of my old teacher.
When I was an undergraduate
at University of Michigan, I took
a course by Professor Kenneth Boulding.
And then, I suppose I'm influenced by him, but he
gave a, when he was elected president of the American
Union, he gave a lecture on the importance of
exchange.
And then, he was elected president of the American
Economic Association.
He gave a talk about economics.
And he had an interesting definition of economics.
What is economics?
There's a lot of definitions
given for the field, but one
definition is the theory of the allocation of scarce
resources, right?
That's by some definition what the essence of economics is.
But Boulding said, that doesn't sound right to him,
but it's the science.
It's about the allocation of scarce resources.
And so is, even the
family is an instrument of scarce
resources.
So, Boulding said in, it was his 1969 presidential address,
that economics is the study of exchange.
All right.
So, obviously, it's prices and quantities that economics
emphasizes, and those are parameters of an exchange.
So, we'll say that equals economics.
I'm reminded of another book.
I'm talking in very general terms first, and then I'm
going to focus in on stock exchanges.
But I'm reminded of another really important book, which I
read so many years ago.
It's called, The Great Exchange.
It's a book by Carl
Polanyi, called The Great Transformation.
And that was written in 1944.
What is the great transformation?
Well, for Polanyi, it's the invention of exchange.
So, what is the most important invention of man?
Maybe it's exchange.
According to his history of humankind, this was a relatively
recent invention, Neolithic, or more recent than that.
He argues that in primitive societies, there is really no
arms length.
So, what is the arm length exchange?
An arms length exchange is one
where you just quote a price
and a quantity, and you don't have any other business.
You know, the price and the quantity sum it up.
It's a business transaction.
But Polanyi argued that until
just something on the order of
10,000 years ago, there were no business transactions.
And so, there was really no gift exchange.
There were relationships people had.
And you would solidify a relationship by making a gift
to someone else.
And then, that person would later reciprocate.
But there's no price, there's no exchange.
So, he claims that the development of our civilization
is really the result of
the development of the idea of
exchange, and then an amplification of the idea, as
it became more and more pervasive.
By the way, I've since
learned, I thought Polanyi was very
impressive, but some anthropologists question
whether there wasn't exchange more than 10,000 years ago.
And they cite evidence.
One kind of evidence that's
found of this is that certain
commodities, even in the Paleolithic times, certain
commodities are found far from where they were mined.
Like flint to make stone
tools, or ochre to make body
paint.
And they figured out where,
you can do a chemical analysis,
and you can figure out where it was mined.
And then, if you find
that it arrived somewhere 1,000 miles
away, there must have been exchange, right?
The cavemen, no?
Okay, it could have been that they just killed someone,
right.
So, I guess nobody knows.
But anyway, some anthropologists argue that there
was exchange.
Maybe it was too pervasive.
Of course, people did kill a
lot of people in those days,
too, anthropologists report.
So, maybe Polanyi had it exactly right.
But I think he had
it at least approximately right, that
exchange has become a bigger
and bigger part of our lives.
And that's modern civilization.
So, I think that's the question.
I think that's the question.
And that's modern civilization.
So, I'm going to talk mostly about financial exchange.
That's the subject of this course.
But I can be a little bit more general.
I wanted to start by distinguishing a broker and a
dealer.
What's the difference?
It's a fundamental thing.
A broker, actually, I've got this almost as a slogan.
A broker acts on behalf of
others as an agent to earn a
commission.
So, it's for others, trades for
others as an agent for a
commission.
So, it's for others, trades for
others as an agent for a
commission.
A commission is a fee.
What is a dealer?
A dealer trades for himself
or herself, acting as a principal,
not an agent, and profits from a markup.
So, I can give you an example of each.
When you buy or sell a
house, do you get a real estate
broker or a real estate dealer?
That's almost obvious, right?
Because you think, you've heard
the term real estate broker so
many times.
When you buy or sell a
house, you commission a broker, and
you agree on a contract
that pays the real estate broker.
A certain sum of money, maybe
6% of the value of the house,
if a buyer is found.
And then the broker doesn't buy your house, right?
So, the broker is an agent.
And the 6% is the commission
that the broker gets, if he or
she is successful in finding
the other side of the deal.
So, that's the real estate broker.
What's an example of a dealer?
An antique dealer.
Right?
Suppose you're buying a chest of drawers for your apartment.
You go to an antique
store, and there's someone there, your
antique dealer, who has furniture that he now owns,
having bought it, and then sells
you and makes a profit by
selling it.
And then the dealer makes a
profit by selling to you at a
higher price, namely, with a markup.
He marks up the price
that he paid for the item.
So, let me just ask
you, why is it that way?
Why are antiques sold by dealers and real estate by
brokers?
I recently had a discussion with Guillermo Ordeñez, who's
an assistant professor here.
He said, well, maybe there are real estate dealers.
Oliver helped us and found, actually, in Germany, a couple
of real estate dealers, but only, like, a couple.
And we couldn't find any in the U.S.
And we searched around in
many other countries, and there was
just virtually none.
No real estate dealers.
Anyone have any idea why?
I'm asking you to think.
Or does anyone come from
a country where they have real
estate dealers?
And that would end it, if
you – I bet not, right?
Well, what about antique brokers?
Why not that?
Have you ever heard of an antique broker?
Maybe there are, you know.
But it's an interesting question.
It seems like some markets are naturally dealer markets, and
some are broker markets.
We thought of one explanation why.
We thought of a market
that was a little bit different.
We thought of an explanation why there aren't real estate
dealers, at least in the United States.
We learned that a dealer has
to pay income tax on the profits
from a deal.
And that is at a higher
rate than a capital gains tax.
And so, that closes people out.
You wouldn't want to be a
real estate dealer, because you end
up paying a higher tax.
The other thing is, I wonder if there's something about
information that someone who deals in real estate – it's
just too hard to know
what to pay for a house.
You know, it's so subjective.
You can make big mistakes if
you're going to buy houses and
then resell them at a markup,
because the market is just so
variable.
And, you know, it ultimately changes quickly.
Maybe, you know, it's too risky.
I don't know.
I'm trying to think.
But, of course, there are
real estate dealers, just very rare.
So, we're going to talk about stock markets.
And which do you think stock markets are?
Are they dealer markets or broker markets?
Well, the answer is both.
And now, it's not as clear.
And I'll come back to this.
The New York Stock Exchange in
New York is a broker market.
Or they would say an auction market.
It's a continuous double auction market, where a broker
facilitates the trades.
The NASDAQ market is a dealer market.
It's a broker market.
It's a dealer market.
So, you pay commissions to your
broker at the New York Stock
Exchange, you pay a markup to your dealer at NASDAQ.
So, I'm just trying to think.
I thought I will start by talking about stock exchange
and historically.
And I have a lot to say.
I can't cover it all.
I was going to start with ancient Rome.
I think I mentioned that before.
But I'm getting there in my notes.
The ancient Roman Stock Exchange is the first stock
exchange that I think anyone knows about.
But traders, I'm relying on the research of Ulrica
Maumandiere, who has studied the ancient Roman Stock
Exchange as much as can be studied.
There's not that much evidence about it.
But the traders met outdoors on
the Roman Forum at the Temple
of Castor.
That's where you went to buy and sell shares.
The shares in Latin were called partes.
I don't know if I covered this or not.
And the companies were called publicani.
And the peculiar nature of the ancient Roman corporations is
that they sold, their customers were the government.
And they were the people who
were the people who were the
customers with the government.
And so, they did services for the government, like provide
horses for the army, or they
would feed the geese on the
Roman Forum, on the Roman capital.
They always fed the geese there, because the geese were
hallow in ancient Rome, because
they once warned of an invasion
by cackling.
So, there was a publicanus
that was in charge of feeding
the geese.
But that seemed to, the
geese were the people who were
the most important people.
And also, they would talk about share prices.
It's known that they would
go up and down, even then.
But there's no data on their share prices.
It seemed that there was a
long gap for stock exchanges after
the fall of the Roman Empire, and the publicani disappeared.
And there were various, there's a wide variety of financial
enrangements.
There were various corporations.
But the advent of, the
rebirth of the stock exchange really
didn't occur until 1602 in Amsterdam, when the, I mentioned
this before, when the Dutch East India Company started
trading.
And then, Jonathan's Coffee House.
I like that story.
In London, lots of people
would get together and talk there.
And coffee houses were, became
a big thing in late 1600s.
And somebody started posting stock prices on the wall at
Jonathan's Coffee House by, what was the date?
And so, the London Stock Exchange
grew out of Jonathan's Coffee House.
And then, moving forward in time, now
we're going to get lots of countries,
but I'll mention the New York Stock Exchange.
The traders of shares in the United States
met outside, and in 1792, under a buttonwood tree.
I'll put buttonwood, that's a curious name.
I think that's just a common
tree that we still have around.
And they signed the agreement to
form the New York Stock Exchange.
But then, what else?
Next in my little history.
India.
By the 1850s, there were in Mumbai, or
then called Bombay, there were traders under a
famous banyan tree.
They're all outdoors in Bombay.
These banyan trees are
more impressive than buttonwood trees.
But it was by 1880.
1875, the Bombay Stock Exchange was founded.
So, that's the BSE.
So, that's been around for over 100 years.
But things have happened more recently.
And one thing that's been shaking things
up, these are very venerable old institutions.
What's been shaking things up
is the advent of electronic trading.
And these were kind
of old-fashioned, venerable institutions.
Do you know what happens
at the New York Stock Exchange?
What happened then and still happens today?
There's a floor called the trading floor.
And the various brokers meet there,
just like in Jonathan's Coffee House.
They actually physically come to
the floor and they stand around.
And there are posts for each stock.
And if today you think you have a customer
who wants to buy IBM stock, then you go over
to the IBM crowd.
And there's a crowd of brokers there who are trading.
And you just do it.
Verbally, you talk to them and you make a trade.
That's really old-fashioned.
There is something more electronic and modern
about the New York Stock Exchange, but that
specialist post behavior still persists.
Most of the world is switching over.
Most of the world is switching over to electronic trading.
And so, things happen that – so, for
example, in India, they developed another stock exchange
called the National Stock Exchange.
And that was in 1992.
And the National Stock Exchange was all electronic.
And so, it was the modern version.
It's rapidly gaining on the Bombay Stock Exchange.
So, let me go a little bit more forward.
China, because of the communist government, did
not have a stock exchange until 1990.
And there were two stock exchanges founded
in China in 1990, Shanghai and Shenzhen.
And at least the Shanghai Stock
Exchange is owned by the Chinese.
And that's why Laura Cha, when she talked to
us about that, she was on the China Securities
Regulatory Commission, which actually
owned the Shanghai Stock Exchange.
So, that's the – oh, Latin America.
Sao Paulo Stock Exchange, 1890.
Mexico has only one stock exchange,
but it was founded in 1894.
So, we seem to have
like two different kinds of exchanges.
We have the old exchanges, at least 100
years old, and we have the new electronic exchanges.
Things have really sped up
with the advent of electronic exchanges.
So, I mentioned the New York Stock Exchange, which started
on the street, outdoors, and is an old-fashioned exchange that –
– that's the New York Stock Exchange.
It's a very old-fashioned exchange
that has been slow to update.
But more recently, we have –
I mentioned it already – NASDAQ.
That's the – it stands for originally
National Association of Securities Dealers Automatic Quotation System,
which was created in the 1970s.
The interesting story about NASDAQ, in the 70s,
the New York Stock Exchange was highly prestigious.
It was the big board, the place.
And a critical element of a stock exchange is that
in order to get your stocks traded on the exchange,
you have to satisfy listing requirements.
So, the New York Stock Exchange would
examine any corporation that wanted to be –
listed on the exchange.
And it was the prestigious, big exchange.
So, it had high standards.
So, the company had to have a history of earnings.
It had to have the right
kind of management structure and board.
A lot of things were checked out by the exchange.
And as a result, the way it would work in the
1970s, a startup company could never get traded on the exchange.
It would be traded instead by
brokers off exchange or over the counter.
So, OTC means over the counter.
That means not on an exchange.
So, in the 1970s and earlier, the over-the-counter brokers would
deal with each other informally with the New York Stock Exchange.
Or actually, out on the street.
They would meet each other out on
the sidewalk originally, and then they got telephones.
And they had some record, which they called pink
sheets, because they were traditionally printed on pink paper.
These were lists of dealers buy and
sell quotes on prices of over-the-counter stocks.
The National Association of Securities
deals with the stock market.
And the dealers then was
an organization of these over-the-counter traders.
And in the early 70s, they
set up the first computerized system.
They decided that everyone's telephoning everybody.
Let's create a system that really
works and that gets us the information.
And so, that was the NASDAQ system.
The first computer-based system, which has now
increasingly taken over much of the world.
I shouldn't imply that New York Stock
Exchange was entirely a laggard on this.
Electronics played a role in stocks going back very early.
The New York Stock Exchange used telegraph
in the 19th century to convey prices.
And they invented ticker tape machines.
A ticker tape machine is an electronic
printer that would print out stock prices.
And in fact, Thomas Edison, the inventor, his
first invention was actually a ticker tape machine.
That was in, I think,
the 1870s that printed stock prices.
But all it was, was a
record of what had traded recently.
It wasn't a system that helped you trade.
It just reported what had happened.
It was historical.
So, I wanted to show you
what NASDAQ created in the 70s.
And it's an order book that would
be visible to everyone who trades on it.
So, prior to discussing that, I want
to tell you about different kinds of orders.
If you buy and sell stock, and you call up
a broker, and you say, I want to buy and sell,
the simplest kind of order is a market order.
And you would specify the quantity.
You would say, I want to buy,
and the name of the company, of course.
I want to buy 100 shares of General
Motors, or I want to sell 100 shares.
But you don't name a price.
You'll find out whatever the price was.
The broker will get you the best price.
If he or she is a good broker,
we'll try to get you the best price.
But it'll still be unknown to
you, because you didn't specify it.
You might be unhappy with the price.
The price might be too high.
And then the broker will say to you,
well, if you're unhappy, you should have told me.
You could have told me not
to pay more than a certain amount.
For a buy.
Or not to take less than
a certain amount for a sell.
So, the alternative is a limit order.
And so, with a limit order,
you give both quantity and price.
So, if it's a buy, I want to buy so many shares,
but I don't want to pay more than such and such a price.
Then the broker will keep that on its mind.
And then you can ask for the price on his or her
books until, well, whatever the agreement between you and the broker is.
It might expire after the day is over.
Or you could ask to
have it kept on the book.
And when the price becomes available, which is no higher
than your specified price, then the order will be executed.
Otherwise, it won't be executed.
And you specify both a quantity and a price,
and the order will be filled or partly filled.
You might not be able to get all of your quantity, but they'll
fill as much as they can of it at that price or lower.
And there's another kind of order called a stop order.
With a stop order, you also specify quantity.
You also specify quantity and price.
But it's different.
With a limit order, you would
buy, say it's a buy limit order.
Well, let's talk about sell.
If it's a sell limit order, you would sell
the quantity at such and such a price or higher.
With a stop order, you would sell that
quantity at such and such a price or lower.
I have to make that clear.
A stop order, also called a stop loss order, is an order that you can
place with the broker to indicate that I'm worried that this stock might really collapse.
I'm holding it, but I want you to
sell it if the price starts falling a lot.
So, suppose the price is 100 today.
I could put a stop loss order at 80.
And then, at least I know I
can't lose more than 20% of my investment.
Because the broker will immediately sell it when
the price of that stock falls below 80.
There's also a buy stop order.
And that would be something that someone would
rationally do if that person had shorted a stock.
So, if you had shorted a stock, and you were
worried that the price would go up and ruin you,
you can leave with your broker a buy stop order
to buy the stock whenever the price exceeds a certain amount.
And you would do that to prevent yourself
from having unlimited losses on your short position.
There's other kinds of orders, but
those are the main kinds of orders.
Now, I wanted to talk particularly about limit orders.
That's the most important kind.
A lot of advisors say, never place a market order.
Why should you ever do a market order?
There's always some price that you'd be unhappy with.
You might as well say that.
And so, some exchanges don't even allow market orders.
So, let's talk about limit orders.
And what I wanted to show you
was what a NASDAQ level 2 customer sees.
NASDAQ is an organization, now it's a
firm traded on its own stock exchange.
It's called NASDAQ OMX.
If you want to subscribe to
NASDAQ, it's very expensive, I understand.
So, you can subscribe at level 1
or level 2, which is more expensive.
I was going to show you an example
of what you would see on your computer screen,
if you subscribe to NASDAQ
level 2 for a particular stock.
And so, this is a
hypothetical limit order book for Microsoft.
And it's a very interesting thing.
What it shows, this is not live,
but it would be live on your screen.
These numbers would be changing before your
eyes, flashing back and forth before your eyes.
And so, I've just frozen
it at a moment in time.
So, what do we have?
We have six columns here.
This first column is the shares.
And this is the shares.
And this is the shares that people want to buy.
So, the first three columns correspond to those.
So, the bid is the price
they're bidding to buy these shares.
Remember, NASDAQ is a dealer market.
So, these dealers are making these bids,
or people are making them through a dealer.
And MPID is the marketplace ID, where
these bids and offers are being made.
So, the first one shown, someone is offering to
buy 100 shares of Microsoft at a price of $25.23.
And that is listed on ARCAX.
ARCAX, there's an interesting, so
I didn't mention that exchange.
It's now part of the New York Stock Exchange.
Maybe I'll come back to that in a minute.
But let me just continue to explain this.
This slide.
Now, you note that the bid
prices are arranged in declining order, right?
They go down as you move down.
The computer has sorted all the orders.
These are all the unfilled orders.
Someone called their broker and said,
I want to buy 100 shares.
And the broker entered the bid through ARCAX.
ARCAX.
And it's now on the NASDAQ screen.
Someone else had a much bigger
buy order, wants to buy 9,430 shares.
And this came in directly to NASDAQ.
But it's a penny less, $25.22.
And so, you can just see what's going down.
Now, the other side of this,
is that clear what we're seeing here?
The other side of the screen is the buy orders.
And it's exactly the same.
Except that here, the buy orders are the same.
Except that here, the numbers go
up as you move down the screen.
Because the computer has sorted them in the reverse order.
So, that represents what various people are willing to buy.
So, somebody is willing to buy 2,400 shares at $25.24.
Okay.
And somebody, well, actually,
there's two different customers.
This one placed the order first.
So, I think that's the problem.
The first one is the priority.
It's by the one who placed it first.
Somebody else at the Cincinnati Exchange, I
guess that's what that means, offered to
buy 8,200 shares at the very same price.
But it's listed as a separate order.
And so on.
So, now, you're sitting here looking at this screen now.
And you notice that this ask price
here is higher than the bid price there.
So, what does that mean to you?
It means there's no trade, right?
Because somebody wants, someone is
offering to sell at $25.24.
And somebody is offering to buy at $25.23.
It's no trade.
Until somebody changes their price.
That's no surprise, because these orders would
be filled very quickly, if there's a crossing.
See, these two lines don't cross.
So, it's like if you plotted these curves.
There's supply and demand curves, right?
We could plot the amount at various prices.
Well, you could see I'd have a
supply and demand curve that don't cross.
Normally, they have to cross somewhere,
and then there's a market-clearing price.
These things normally don't cross, because if they
did cross, it would immediately disappear from the screen.
Someone would finish the order and then sell.
But you sitting at the screen now have
a pretty good idea what the price is.
A NASDAQ Level 2 is better than a NASDAQ Level
1, because Level 1 just gives you the first row.
It's cheaper to subscribe to that.
What NASDAQ Level 1 gives you is the inside spread.
It would tell you that there is $100.
And then, if you want to hit that
order, you could take either side of that.
But it doesn't tell you the whole picture.
If you know NASDAQ Level 2, you
know a lot more about the market.
And if you're going to play the
game of trading, you want to know this.
So, for example, you know that it might be
hard for a price to fall rapidly below $0.25.
But if you're going to play the
game of trading, you want to know this.
It's going to fall below $25.22,
because there's a big buyer down there.
And so, it's going to be hard
for the price to fall below that.
If you saw the screen in real life, these
numbers would be just blinking, changing rapidly before you.
And trades that were there 20 seconds
ago would be gone in a flash.
So, you've got to move fast to execute these trades.
On a fully automated system,
the trades would be executed automatically.
And this is becoming, electronic
trading is taking over the world.
And the orders can be executed
by computers that make it instant.
So that you don't even, the number doesn't even appear
on the screen long enough for you to see it.
So, one development that's coming up.
So, you've got to move fast to execute these trades.
And the next one that's coming in
now is what's called high frequency trading.
HFT, which is trading that is done by computers.
Once you have a system like this, when you have to
trade through a floor broker on the New York Stock Exchange,
it has to proceed at human pace, right?
So, you make a telephone call to your broker.
Your broker makes another telephone call to the representative
on the floor of the New York Stock Exchange.
That person walks over to the crowd and
then discusses, indicates what, it's like a poker game.
You don't want to reveal your hand,
but you kind of feel people out.
And then after a little discussion, you reach a trade.
But when you have something that you can
hit on a computer, it just goes instantly.
And then you'll start programming trading.
And that's been an important phenomenon, because you
see these things moving faster than you can.
These prices disappear and reappear so fast that
you can't quite know, you can't act fast enough.
So, we have algorithmic trading or program trading.
And so, that goes back to practically to the 1970s.
Certainly by the 80s, program trading
was becoming a big and important phenomenon.
And it's becoming increasingly important now.
High-frequency trading now, brokers will
invoke what are called millisecond strategies.
You can actually flash an order.
You can actually flash an order on some of
the exchanges that lasts a thousandth of a second.
You can put a buy order or a
sell order and retract it in a millisecond.
And that means, this would be
a trading strategy, which you might employ.
You could do that to discourage people from trading.
If you want to trade only with the computers,
if you think, people are too smart for me.
I don't want to trade with people.
I want to rip off the computers.
Then you write a millisecond trading strategy.
You can sort into who trades with you.
Now, the interesting thing about millisecond trading
is that it's favoring the electronic exchanges.
More and more, as time goes on, people
are getting more and more sophisticated about high-frequency trading.
And so, they want to trade on exchanges that are
fully electronic, so that they can play all of these games.
And that means that the floor exchanges
are dying out over most of the world.
By the way, the New York Stock Exchange, I
was going to give you a history of it.
The New York Stock Exchange has
been slow to adapt to these technologies.
Let me just give you a little history.
Electronic trading is an exciting thing for many people.
But I think it started.
The really interesting electronic trading started
with the ECNs, electronic communication networks,
that were allowed by the Securities and
Exchange Commission as alternatives to stock exchanges.
Stock exchanges are highly regulated
by governments around the world.
But in the 1990s, the
Securities and Exchange Commission allowed more,
sophisticated electronic trading, at least as an experiment.
So, they didn't call these
things exchanges, they called them ECNs.
And one of the most important
ECNs was a company called Archipelago.
Another one was called Island.
These were actually just websites where you could trade.
And they were open to the public.
They had a different approach.
They had a different culture.
They had more of a web culture.
The web culture is, we're not going
to charge you to see the order book.
We'll just put it out to everybody.
The web doesn't charge you for a lot of things.
And so, they became popular
trading sites for the general public.
They grew up the way the personal computer grew.
So, New York Stock Exchange,
when they first saw Archipelago,
they said, oh, this is a bunch of
college kids fooling around, some computer game, sort of.
And they didn't think about it.
They didn't take it seriously.
But eventually, New York Stock
Exchange had to take it seriously,
because Archipelago was growing so fast.
So, eventually, New York
Stock Exchange merged with Archipelago.
And so, they're now, I think
most of their trades go through ArcaX.
I'm not sure if that's right, but a
large fraction of their trades go through ArcaX.
And so, New York Stock Exchange bought Archipelago in 2005.
And at that time, ArcaX was breathing close
on New York Stock Exchange for trading volume.
And so, they were able to get the stock.
Things are happening fast in the
stock exchange, because the technology is changing.
Whereas, we had the New York
Stock Exchange in the old days,
it was this single prestigious exchange that lasted
for over 150 years without any substantive change.
But now, electronic trading is coming
in, and everything is being shaken up.
So, the New York Stock
Exchange merged with Archipelago in 2005.
And then, they did another merger, let's
say, the New York Stock Exchange with Euronext,
which is another exchange in Europe, in 2006.
And right now, they're going
through a merger, another merger process.
Apparently, with the Deutsche Bank.
And that's 2011.
It's not finalized yet.
And now, NASDAQ is making an
offer for the New York Stock Exchange.
And so, is another
exchange called the Intercontinental Exchange.
But the little guys are
buying up the old-time big guys.
Laura Cha was saying in her lecture, she said,
that we used to think
of stock exchanges as like utilities.
Each country has its own stock exchange.
It's the pride of each country.
But now, it's not happening anymore.
And this reflects a bigger and broader trend,
that economies are becoming more
and more integrated across the world.
So, the idea that there will be a
stock exchange for each country is becoming dated.
So, the New York Stock Exchange
is a new kind of stock exchange.
may soon be a German company.
But that's what happens in modern times.
So, now, I wanted to talk
about some problems with high frequency trading.
As things get so electronic,
let me give you one example.
In 1987, this was the early days of electronic trading.
But still, it had advanced pretty far.
On October 19th of 1987,
the stock markets in the United
States fell, according to the S&P 500,
over 20% in one month.
In one day.
The government did a study.
President Reagan ordered a study
and put it in charge of Nicholas Brady.
And so, the so-called Brady Commission did
a report on why the stock market,
that was the biggest single
stock market drop in U.S. history.
And the Brady Commission did a report
on that stock market drop.
And concluded that program trading, computer trading,
had played a big role in the drop.
There had been a development of programs
that were called portfolio insurance,
sell strategies.
They called it portfolio insurance.
But it wasn't really insurance.
It was an automatic sell strategy.
It's like a stop-loss order,
but a more sophisticated one.
That could be executed in continuous time by a program.
And that led to an instability in the market
that was not anticipated and shocked the world.
So, the Brady Commission made a number of recommendations.
Notably, the Commission recommended that
the exchanges impose trading halts.
That would prevent stocks from dropping,
the whole market from crashing.
So, the New York Stock Exchange and other exchanges,
after the Brady Commission report,
instituted what are called circuit breakers.
And these are automatic market halts
that stop the market when prices are falling,
to help prevent another 1987,
type stock market crash.
So, now, the system is getting complicated.
Even before this,
the United States government had created,
had passed a set of rules
in response to complaints
about people not being given a share of the stock.
And they were not given the best price.
So, here's the problem.
We have multiple exchanges.
New York Stock Exchange is one of many.
And if you call a stock broker,
the stock broker doesn't,
has discretion over where,
which exchange the broker will use to fill your order.
And so, the broker might choose an exchange
that doesn't give you the best price.
And the broker can, in effect,
rip you off as a broker.
In fact, there's a practice
called the payment for order flow.
So, a stock broker,
who is receiving orders from retail clients,
may find that there is a dealer
that's willing to pay for order flow.
When a customer asks to buy the stock,
don't put it through the New York Stock Exchange.
Give it to me,
and I'll give you, the broker,
a fee for directing the order my way.
And that may not serve the client well,
because the client then
might end up paying a higher price.
So, there were a lot of complaints about this.
And it's a difficult problem,
because it's hard to monitor everything that people do.
And there might be justifications
for a payment for order flow.
But there have been efforts
to try to make it a fairer system.
And in 1975,
the U.S. Congress set up something called
the National Market System.
And, oops, I think,
so,
the NMS is the National Market System,
and the ITS is the Intermarket Trading System.
What the government in the United States did,
is it said that brokers
have to get the best price,
or it's called best bid, best offer,
best bid for their clients.
And they have a responsibility for their clients
to take the market with the best price.
So, in conjunction with this,
the exchanges built something called
the Consolidated Quotation System
that allows brokers to see prices on various exchanges
and direct the order of the client
to the exchange that's showing up
during the best price.
So, that is a system that was started
in the United States in 1975.
And brokers still have an obligation
to get the best price for their customers,
regardless of exchange.
But the obligation is hard for the government
to monitor and it gets complicated.
For example, if you're confronting this system,
and your broker wants
500 shares, well, I can't fill them all
at the same price, right?
Well, actually, I could here.
If the broker wanted 10,000 shares,
they'd be all different prices,
because I have all these different customers, right?
I'm asking different amounts.
So, what do you want us to do, SEC?
And so, the SEC recently clarified this,
I think it was in 2006.
Well, we only mean the amount
that you have to hit this, the best one.
There's one up here, 2400 for 2524.
How you fill the others, we can't get into that.
So, it's not a complete protection for customers,
but there still is this obligation
for brokers to use the national market system
to get the best price.
But the system is complicated and confusing,
because there's so many computers involved,
there's so many different exchanges,
and there's so many rules.
It's hard for people to keep up with it.
So, I had on the reading
list, I had a report that I,
well, I found the report.
It was very much in the news a while back.
This is a report on May 6, 2010.
You remember what happened then?
That was not that long ago.
The stock market, as of around 2.30 in the afternoon
in the United States, had fallen 4%.
And then, within a matter of minutes,
it dropped another 6%.
And then, it rebounded quickly.
Some individual stocks dropped practically
to nothing.
And you could buy, you know,
a $30 stock for 30 cents
or something like that.
And then, they rebounded.
So, what happened?
Why did we have this very
brief crash in the stock markets?
It wasn't like 1987, where the market went down
and stayed down.
If you look at closing prices, nothing much happened.
It was this brief.
A glitch, which probably cost
some people huge amounts of money.
Because if you were trading right at that moment,
you'd have a problem.
So, I have as an
optional reading on the reading list,
a study that was made of May 6, 2010,
by the SEC and the Commodity Futures Trading Commission,
trying to understand what happened then.
And the study does focus on high-frequency trading.
There were a lot of computers trading automatically
at that moment in time.
So, what apparently happened on May 6 is,
the market was already in a stressed mode
before 2.30 p.m.
The VIX index had shot up.
There was some bad news.
The market was down 4%.
So, that meant that some traders were wondering,
what's going on?
And maybe they decided to drop out for a while
and just be cautious.
But the computers were still trading.
And then something happened.
The computers started trading
back and forth in milliseconds.
And I don't know what
the programs were supposed to do,
or what they, maybe nobody knows the whole picture.
But the volume of trade
just went to an astronomical level.
And it scared people off.
And so, there were a lot
of trading pauses that were put.
Exchanges have rules about that.
And individual dealerships have rules about that.
And dealers will say, I'm dropping out.
I see all this volume.
I'm not in here anymore.
So, it remains that the trading that was left
was substantially computer trading.
And the market became very illiquid.
And so, this study has recommended fixes for this.
But it doesn't recommend ending high-frequency trading.
A lot of people would recommend doing that.
There's a popular anger, especially since
this May 6, 2010 crisis occurred
during the period of financial crisis.
And people kind of imagine that the two are linked.
I think they're kind of independent.
I think the May 6, 2010 phenomenon
was due to some kind of anomalies
or infamiliarity with high-frequency trading.
It's a glitch.
And not a major fault.
But it led to a
lot of anger about high-frequency trading.
But I've talked to some
people at the Chicago Mercantile Exchange
and others who think that the
public anxiety over high-frequency trading is misplaced.
It's kind of inevitable.
The future is computers, right?
They're replacing people all over.
Not in a judgment thing.
You know, someone was saying at
the CME meeting where I was,
that the basic business that we're doing is
still the same as it was 100 years ago.
But now we have laptops, right?
It's just like when you write a term paper.
It's basically the same thing that somebody
would have done with a feather pen
and a piece of paper 200 years ago, right?
It's basically the same.
But we live in a computer age
now, and we don't want to go back.
And so, high-frequency trading means that
we have to be a little careful.
Things can happen with lightning speed.
But we'll learn.
There hasn't been another May 6, 2010 since.
It was just an anomaly because people
were unfamiliar with that kind of event.
And so, I think it will be all right.
And one thing that it does,
however, is it's changing the geography.
It used to be that in the 90s,
in the 18th century,
a stockbroker had to live in
London or Paris or New York
in order to be close to the trading, right?
Because they didn't have any way to make phone calls.
When they invented the telephone, people said, fine,
I don't have to live in New York anymore.
I can live in anywhere, and I
can just send my call by telephone.
But now, high-frequency trading is bringing it back
that people have to live close to the exchange
because the trading goes so fast
that your electronic signal,
if you try to set up
a high-frequency trading operation in St. Louis,
and you're operating by wire to New York,
the time it takes for electricity to
get from St. Louis to New York
is too big, and you
will be behind on the trade.
So, you want to get as
close as physically possible to the exchange,
to the computer.
You don't, see, the regional exchanges,
there used to be exchanges
in every U.S., big U.S. city.
And they were there, and they were there,
because of social reasons,
that people in Chicago wanted to
talk to a broker in Chicago.
They wanted to be able to
go to his office and see him.
So, there were social reasons for connection.
But now, we're coming up with a new electronic reason.
And because of basic theoretical physics,
you can't move anything faster than the speed of light.
This is going to be with us,
now that we have microsecond trading.
So, I wanted to talk a little bit now,
and I think maybe this will be the last topic,
about how you think about trading as a dealer,
who is confronted with this kind of book.
And as a dealer, you
can put orders on this book,
and enter them, and leave them there.
That's basically what you do.
So, you see various dealers, and their names are shown.
And, for example, well, I
don't know who these people are,
but each dealer is going to
be posting a bid and an ask.
Right?
And a quantity for these.
And it's going to be, if you do this,
you're sitting at your NASDAQ screen,
and you're a dealer.
You can enter your own number on either of these,
either the bid or the ask, or both of them.
So, you have your own bid-ask spread.
Okay?
It's the same thing as an antique dealer.
An antique dealer has an idea,
maybe it's not posted,
of how much he or she
will pay for a chest of drawers
from a Yale student at the end of the semester,
and how much he will charge to sell that.
And the difference between the ask and the bid
is called the spread, or the bid-ask spread.
And so, I wanted to just think
a little bit about the theory of this.
And how do you decide,
of the bid-ask spread,
of what to do?
And why is it what it is?
The spreads are obviously very tight here,
because they're off only by one cent
between the, on the inside spread.
But it doesn't correspond to one person.
Maybe some of these are market,
or customer orders and aren't dealers.
But think of placing an order as a dealer
and leaving it on the screen,
so that anybody can come and,
the risk that you face is that
you will be picked off
by people with superior information.
And let me put it in
the context of an antique dealer.
One thing that antique dealers don't like
is when professional antique dealers
come shopping in their store.
So, what do they do?
You know, if you're a good antique dealer,
you go to all the antique stores,
and you try to disguise yourself,
because they don't want you,
if you're a dealer.
What do you do?
You look through all their stuff,
and you find anything that's mispriced.
You know, there'll be some chest of drawers
that you recognize as an 18th century,
you know, by a famous furniture maker.
So, you buy that at the guy's price.
You pick him off, right?
So, he doesn't want to be picked off,
because somebody will come by who knows more,
will pick off all the good stuff and buy it,
and leave you with the junk.
So, how do you prevent that?
Well, you might think that you could prevent it
by just being smarter,
but you can try.
Try to be as smart as you want,
and read up about all the antiques,
but it's impossible.
You cannot be the smartest guy out there.
Impossible.
There's just too many antiques,
and there's too much inside information.
So, that means you have to set your bid-ask spread
wide enough that you can be picked off
and still make a profit.
You know you're going to get picked off.
And it's the same for stocks.
If you're going to put a
bid-ask spread up on the screen
for some stock,
you're just a sitting duck,
because there'll be some news story
that's either good or bad.
And if it's either way,
somebody else is going to hear of it first.
And when you get a hit on your order,
it's going to be deadly,
because it'll be at the wrong time for you.
So, that's the theory that
you have to make the order,
the bid-ask spread wide enough.
Now, I wanted to then just
give you a little bit of math.
I shouldn't end the lecture on mathematics,
but that's what I'm doing here this time.
And I wanted to just talk
about the frustrating life as a dealer.
I was telling you about frustrations
in life as an investment banker.
There are different frustrations in life as a dealer.
And I'll tell you what the difference is.
Life as a dealer is very different
than life as an employee of something.
You are a dealer, and
you have whatever money you make.
And the problem is, you can get ruined.
This is a classic.
In other words, you can be
working as a dealer for 20 years,
and you see your portfolio growing,
because you're making a lot of money selling.
But, you know, all it
takes is a few bad moves,
and you can be wiped out.
You know, 20 years of work, and you are ruined.
So, I wanted to just think about that.
And this is my last bit of mathematics.
It's a mathematics of gamblers' ruin.
And it's also a mathematics of dealers' ruin.
And so, here's the theory.
If I start out with S
dollars, S is my initial amount of
money as a dealer, OK?
And let's say, I take a
series of bets, which have a
probability, P is the probability of a win.
OK.
What is the?
Probability of eventual ruin.
And if I make one dollar on
each win, and I lose a dollar
on each, minus one on each
loss, I'm doing a sequence of
bets on each loss, all right?
What is the probability that I will eventually be ruined?
OK.
That probability, and I'm not
going to derive this, but it's
simple to derive, actually.
1 minus P over P to the S
power, if P is greater than a half.
OK.
So, I'm going to do a series of bets.
And I'm going to do a series of bets.
So, if my probability of winning is a half, the
probability of my being ruined eventually is one.
And if my probability of
winning is less than a half,
my probability of being ruined eventually is one.
And if my probability of winning
is less than a half, my
probability of being ruined is also one.
I have to somehow raise
the probability of winning on each
particular sale above a half.
But even if I do that, if
I make it, say, 0.6, if I make
probability 60% on one bet, then
1 minus 0.6 is 0.4 over 0.6.
Then my probability of eventual
ruin, starting out with $1, is
4.6, if I did that right.
It goes down with the number
of dollars I start, but it never
goes to zero.
So, the theory of a dealer is
that a dealer has to be thinking
about being ripped off.
I've got to set my
bid-ask spread high enough that the
probability of winning on each
of these little trades that I
make is sufficiently high.
So, if I make a bet
above a half, that my eventual ruin
probability is satisfactorily low for me.
But it's never going to be zero.
This is the irony of being a dealer.
You don't sleep well at night,
because you never know that it
won't eventually unwind.
You don't know that you're
going to lose all the business,
because you can't just set
your bid-ask spread arbitrarily high,
because then you'll lose all the business to other people.
So, you've got to kind of
fix the bid-ask spread enough that
you get business, but you don't
want to fix it too narrowly, so
that this probability falls too
close to a half, because then
you're courting the risk of disaster and eventually having
all of your life's work being wiped out.
So, that was kind of a
quick description of the – I'm saying
different personalities go into different parts of finance.
You have to be kind of
a game player, someone who is not
bothered by the possibility of
eventual ruin in order to go
into becoming a dealer.
Very different from other aspects of financial life.
All right, I'll see you soon
with – we're getting close to
the end of the semester.
Some wrap-up lecture is coming.